Guide to the Party of the Right, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Party of the Right, Yale University, records
1955-2011
RU 1101
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The materials consist of party correspondence, minutes, articles, research papers, debate materials, and a whip list. There are also research papers, debate web sheets, party constitution, event ephemera, speeches, and news articles.
Yale University. Party of the Right
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were transferred from the Party of the Right, 2004 and the Federalist Party, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
Records of the Party of the Right is closed. Researchers must secure in writing a statement from the sitting Chairman of the Party of the Right to access these materials.
Biographical / Historical
One of the seven parties of the Yale Political Union, the Party of the Right was founded in 1953 by dissatisfied members of the original Conservative Party (later re-christened as the Independent Party) after that Party had endorsed Adlai Stevenson as "the conservative candidate for President." By the end of the 1950s many of the Party's enduring traditions had already been established, although it was not until the 1960s that the party really began to understand itself as "Conservatism reborn in Brotherhood." Due to a membership that included conservatives of every stripe, the Party found a dynamic tension between Libertarians and Traditionalists in the early 1970s that has been its hallmark for decades.
Membership in the Party of the Right is elective and lasts "for life at least." Despite this promise, certain members disaffected by the political process left to form both the Tory and Conservative Parties of the Yale Political Union in 1971 and 1996 respectively.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of party correspondence, minutes, articles, research papers, debate materials, and a whip list. There are also research papers, debate web sheets, party constitution, event ephemera, speeches, and news articles.
Related Materials Note
Yale Political Union Records (RU 248). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
College students -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Party of the Right; Yale University. Yale Political Union
- Party of the Right records, Circa 1955-2004; Accession 2004-A-169
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until January 1, 2040.
  - Correspondence to P.H. Burr (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Whip list (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Magazine (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - History, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Special Committee Minutes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Calliopean Society (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Conservative Answer To Pollution" by Frank S. Meyer & John C. Meyer, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, 1975-2011; Accession 2012-A-084
  Scope and Contents
  Accession 2012-A-084 contains one box of organizational records of the Federalist Party which includes a copy of the party constitution and associated materials documenting its creation, event ephemera of various political parties of the Yale Political Union, research papers, web sheets announcing debates and debate topics, meeting minutes, speeches, correspondence, and news articles.
  Restricted until January 1, 2046.
  - Event ephemera - Yale Political Union parties, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Federalist Party Constitution - correspondence and meeting minutes, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News articles, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Research papers
    - A History of the Party of the Right by Peter Haskell Burr and John Cornford Meyer, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A History of the Tory Party at Yale University, 1973-1978 by W.A. Smith, Jr., Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A History of the Tory Independent Party, 1969-1973 by Kevin McKeegan, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reflections of a Tory Legacy Part I: A Recounting of The Glory Days and War, Fall 1985-Fall 1990 by Joseph M. Ditkoff, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Tory Party: From Pre-History to Independence by Thomas Edward Veal, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Unmaking of a Political Union President by Robertson Morrow, 1987 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Speeches and correspondence, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tory Party/Federalist Party - Meeting minutes, debate caucus sheets, speeches and correspondence, 1985, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Web sheets, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 12)